<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavvyer of Lincolnes-Inne reformed: or, An apology for the army. Occasioned by IX queries, upon the printed charge of the army, against the XI members, and the papers thereto annexed; submitted to the publique consideration of all lovers of justice, truth, parliaments, army, and their native countrey. / By the author of The case of the kingdome, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E395_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862136</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E395[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavvyer of Lincolnes-Inne reformed: or, An apology for the army. Occasioned by IX queries, upon the printed charge of the army, against the XI members, and the papers thereto annexed; submitted to the publique consideration of all lovers of justice, truth, parliaments, army, and their native countrey. / By the author of The case of the kingdome, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author of The case of the kingdome, &amp;c. = Marchamont Nedham.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Prynne, William. IX queries upon the printed charge of the army against the XI. members and the papers thereto annexed (Wing P4023).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  IX queries upon the printed charge of the army against the XI. members and the papers thereto annexed --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114285:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114285:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAVVYER OF LINCOLNES-INNE REFORMED: OR, An Apology for the Army.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by IX <hi>Queries,</hi> upon the Printed Charge of the Army, againſt the XI Members, and the Papers thereto annexe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; ſubmitted to the publique conſideration of all Lovers of Juſtice, Truth, Parliaments, Army, and their native Countrey.</p>
            <p>By the Author of <hi>The Caſe of the Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 62.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They only conſult to caſt him down from his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, they delight in lies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114285:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114285:2"/>
            <head>The Lawyer of LINCOLNES-INNE Reformed.</head>
            <p>SInce this Learned <hi>Gentlemans</hi> uſuall way of <hi>Queries,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue rather a diſeaſe of <hi>ill concoction</hi> in the <hi>Brain,</hi> than any <hi>reaſonable</hi> Concluſion of what He undertakes, and is but a piece of <hi>Leiger-du-maine</hi> to <hi>amuſe</hi> mens <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings,</hi> by feeding the <hi>Phantaſie</hi> with ſuch <hi>Feares</hi> and <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies,</hi> as the <hi>weaker</hi> ſort of men (fruitfull enough in theſe times) <hi>create</hi> unto Themſelves out of what they read, rather than any <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to the more <hi>ſolid</hi> part of the <hi>world:</hi> Give leave then to <hi>wonder,</hi> how He or any man <hi>dare</hi> owne ſo much <hi>Impudence</hi> and <hi>Virulence</hi> in ſuch a Time as this, againſt ſo <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> ſo <hi>religious,</hi> ſo <hi>reſolute,</hi> ſo <hi>well-accompliſh't, well-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd,</hi> and <hi>victorious</hi> an Army; the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of whoſe <hi>proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> as it triumphs beyond <hi>Apologie</hi> (being <hi>back't</hi> with all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of an <hi>Honourable</hi> policy, and undeniable <hi>expedients</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi>) ſo it muſt <hi>indeare</hi> them to the <hi>preſent,</hi> and ſhall <hi>innoble</hi> them to all <hi>future</hi> generations.</p>
            <p>Therefore touching the firſt of theſe <hi>Cob-web</hi>-contrivanes by way of <hi>Querie,</hi> wherein thoſe <hi>unſpotted Letters</hi> and <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> from the <hi>Army</hi> (no leſſe admirable for <hi>Stile</hi> than <hi>Equity</hi>) are moſt <hi>maliciouſly</hi> traduced as of <hi>dangerous Conſequence;</hi> and the incomparable <hi>Generall, Officers,</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> taxed of <hi>Arbitrarineſſe,</hi> and <hi>breach of the Houſes privileges,</hi> becauſe thoſe <hi>Declarations</hi> and Charge againſt the Members went to the <hi>Preſſe</hi> without <hi>Leave</hi> from the <hi>Houſe;</hi> I ſuppoſe the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> approbation of men, and the ſudden <hi>deſertion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Members</hi> (Argument enough of <hi>guilt</hi>) will clearely evince, that their <hi>Complaints</hi> were not <hi>cauſeleſſe,</hi> but of <hi>onely</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>Conſequence</hi> to the <hi>Intereſt, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, againſt all <hi>foraigne</hi> Incroachments of thoſe, whoſe <hi>practice</hi> is, under <hi>pretence of Reformation,</hi> by themſelves and ſome <hi>Apoſtate</hi> (with many deluded) <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents,</hi> to make what <hi>Mercats</hi> they pleaſe of the <hi>Publique,</hi> to ſerve <hi>private</hi> ends. And further, it is time to conſider what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114285:3"/>
               <hi>manner</hi> of men theſe are, and what <hi>Tyranny</hi> they would not execute (were their <hi>power</hi> anſwerable to thoſe bitter <hi>paſſions,</hi> which they give us a <hi>Taſte</hi> of upon every <hi>leaſt</hi> occaſion) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they interpret ſo <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>harmeleſſe</hi> an Act in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> as a bare permiſſion of their <hi>Papers</hi> to the Preſſe, into a ſenſe of <hi>Arbitrarineſſe</hi> and <hi>breach of Privilege;</hi> whereas they have done nothing this way, but what is moſt <hi>equitable</hi> in order to their owne <hi>vindication,</hi> and ſatisfaction of the whole <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> whoſe ignorance of the grounds of their ſo <hi>meritorious</hi> Ingagement, might have made them capable to entertaine any <hi>monſtrous impreſſions</hi> and <hi>repreſentations</hi> whatſoever, againſt the <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Army.</hi> And truely, it is high time alſo, that ſome <hi>Courſe</hi> were taken for <hi>ſtating</hi> the <hi>Privileges</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> into <hi>certaine</hi> Limits, that men may no longer <hi>wander</hi> in this <hi>particular,</hi> as in a <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> or <hi>Maze,</hi> nor run upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Turne of <hi>humour</hi> and <hi>diſcontent,</hi> to ſecure themſelves and their <hi>Deſignes,</hi> in the <hi>various, endleſſe,</hi> and <hi>inviſible</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth of <hi>Parliamentary privilege.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the ſecond <hi>Querie,</hi> wherein the <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> are ſaid to be the ſame with <hi>Jack Cade</hi> and his <hi>rebellious popular Army,</hi> and ſo an <hi>Argument</hi> is founded upon this <hi>Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> on that <hi>Statute</hi> of 31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Cade,</hi> to nullifie the <hi>Charge</hi> againſt the <hi>Members</hi> now <hi>Impeached, viz.</hi> that ALL INDITEMENTS (or Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) IN TIME COMMING IN LIKE CASE, UNDER POWER OF TYRANNY, REBELLION, or STIRRING HAD, SHALL BE OF NO RECORD NOR EFFECT, BUT VOID IN LAW; <hi>and ſo not to be received now by the Parliament till the Army be disbanded.</hi> An <hi>Argument</hi> as rare, as the <hi>mad</hi> Impudence of thoſe many <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>inhumane</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions wherewith he hath <hi>beſpattered</hi> his <hi>Paper,</hi> is <hi>horrid</hi> and <hi>unpardonable!</hi> But firſt, to <hi>wipe</hi> away that of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unknown to all men, that as this <hi>Army</hi> behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſo much <hi>Temper,</hi> that few where they come have Cauſe to complaine of <hi>wrong</hi> or <hi>dammage,</hi> ſo the Principall <hi>motive</hi> of their thus <hi>Ingaging</hi> is, to <hi>Cruſh</hi> that <hi>Serpent</hi> in the <hi>Shel,</hi> which (if <hi>hatched</hi> to <hi>maturitie</hi>) would have given an <hi>irrecoverable</hi> wound to <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Libertie;</hi> and as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114285:3"/>
               <hi>Kingly power</hi> muſt have beene rendred as <hi>contemptible</hi> here, as the ſame <hi>deſigne</hi> hath made it beyond <hi>Tweed;</hi> ſo the <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of the <hi>ſubject</hi> muſt have <hi>dwindled</hi> into the ſame miſery, leanneſſe, and povertie, or worſe than many of our poore <hi>Countrymen</hi> doe ſuffer, as <hi>ſlaves</hi> under the power of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the ſecond <hi>gudgeon</hi> which this <hi>bookiſh</hi> mad-man hath fiſh't out of the <hi>ſtatute,</hi> for his <hi>friends</hi> to <hi>ſwallow</hi> in opinion againſt the <hi>Army;</hi> It is a moſt ſenſeleſſe thing to call that a <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> when men doe Act meerly for thoſe <hi>Ends,</hi> whereto they were firſt <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> by <hi>Parliament,</hi> againſt a <hi>viſible Plot</hi> of <hi>particular</hi> men on foot, to amuſe, abuſe, and ſurprize the <hi>Parliament</hi> under-hand ſo farre, as to make them upon <hi>miſ-informations,</hi> contribute toward the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> and themſelves, in diſ-counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing and <hi>diſ-contenting</hi> this <hi>Army;</hi> to whom (next under God) the <hi>Nation</hi> muſt owe the re-inveſtiture of <hi>freedome,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>ſecret</hi> underminings of all ſuch <hi>darke-lanthorne</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots. For, though their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> make an <hi>Advantage</hi> by ſcandalizing them as enemies to the Privileges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> (which is the maine deſigne of our <hi>Sottiſh</hi> Lawyer throughout his <hi>Queries</hi>) yet it cannot be ſo taken, ſince the <hi>Charge</hi> reflects onely upon a <hi>prevailing</hi> partie of <hi>private</hi> Intereſts, many of which have <hi>unduely</hi> crept into the <hi>Houſe</hi> to ſerve <hi>by-ends,</hi> and over-awe the more <hi>Noble</hi> Partie; and ſo being in this <hi>deſperate</hi> condition, think to <hi>ſhelter</hi> themſelves under the notion of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary privilege,</hi> that they may with the more <hi>libertie</hi> and <hi>ſecuritie,</hi> contrive the ruine of thoſe <hi>greater ends,</hi> for whoſe protection and preſervation they were firſt admitted or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi>) ſo that the <hi>Army</hi> in accuſing the Heads of theſe men, cannot be ſaid to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe the <hi>Privileges</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> but rather to preſerve them, leſt through the <hi>infection</hi> of <hi>corrupt</hi> Members, they be tainted with <hi>Infamy,</hi> by being extended to countenance <hi>private</hi> wrongs or <hi>publique</hi> miſchiefe. Nor is this onely a <hi>ſurmiſe</hi> to gaine a good opinion of the <hi>Army;</hi> for that needs not, ſeeing their <hi>Intentions</hi> are ſo apprehended by <hi>moſt</hi> people of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> not onely in point of the <hi>Houſes privileges,</hi> but alſo in relation to the common <hi>freedome</hi> of the <hi>ſubject,</hi> with a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114285:4"/>of the <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> with ſuch <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>freedome,</hi> as may gaine a laſting <hi>Repute</hi> to thoſe Acts that ſhall be provided for by the <hi>Royall Aſſent,</hi> in that behalfe: which (to the joy and happineſſe of all true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> that have not loſt themſelves in a <hi>Scottiſh-Miſt</hi>) wil prove the bleſſed conſequence of that <hi>unparallel'd</hi> piece of Vertue in the Army, which is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciouſly <hi>blaſted</hi> with a Story of <hi>Iack Cade,</hi> and a <hi>phrentick</hi> ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the third <hi>Querie,</hi> wherein the <hi>Charge</hi> is excepted againſt, as too <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>ambiguous,</hi> againſt eleven <hi>eminent Members, moſt of which have done gallant ſervice in the field, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to particulars of perſons, fact, time, place, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo a <hi>moſt illegall, injurious, arbitrary accuſation and proceeding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Rules of Juſtice and Equity:</hi> I ſhall extract ſeverall <hi>Paſſages</hi> out of the <hi>Armies</hi> owne <hi>Papers,</hi> in juſtification of their <hi>Charge</hi> againſt all prejudice and calumny; as firſt, the <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of the <hi>Charge</hi> it ſelfe (if the <hi>eager Gentleman</hi> had not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look't it) might have ſatisfied him that they intended not to dwell upon <hi>Generals,</hi> though it were firſt offered in ſuch <hi>termes,</hi> but deſcend to make good in <hi>particulars,</hi> each <hi>Head</hi> againſt <hi>ſome</hi> of the Perſons, and ſome one <hi>head</hi> or more againſt <hi>each</hi> of the Perſons; and ſhortly to give in the ſeverall <hi>particulars</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt each Perſon reſpectively, and make them good by <hi>proofes,</hi> when the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> ſhould admit thereof; the <hi>Army</hi> deſiring to have and <hi>reſerve</hi> to themſelves, the liberty of exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any <hi>farther</hi> Charge againſt <hi>all</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare alſo the words of the laſt <hi>Declaration</hi> from the <hi>Army,</hi> which ſay; <q>Whereas many of the things whereto the <hi>Charge</hi> relates, are things <hi>ſpoken, moved,</hi> or <hi>done</hi> in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> ſo as we have yet no <hi>cleare</hi> way opened, particularly to <hi>Charge</hi> or mention Them, or to produce <hi>proofes</hi> to Them, without ſome <hi>pretence</hi> againſt us of <hi>breach of Priviledge;</hi> and therefore (though we thinke no <hi>priviledge</hi> ought to <hi>protect</hi> evill men in doing wrong to <hi>particulars,</hi> or miſchiefe to the <hi>publique,</hi> yet) we have been hitherto ſo tender of <hi>Parliament Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> as that we have only <hi>Remonſtrated</hi> the <hi>evill</hi> of ſuch things done; and ſuppoſing the <hi>Houſe</hi> to have been (as we did and do beleeve, and if way were open without <hi>breach of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114285:4"/>ſhould not doubt to prove it was) ſome waies <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed, deluded, ſurprized,</hi> or otherwiſe abuſed in thoſe things by <hi>evill Members,</hi> we have frequently in former <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> (before the <hi>Charge</hi>) put the <hi>Parliament</hi> upon it (who without colour of <hi>breach of Privilege</hi> might do it) to find out and <hi>diſcover</hi> who they were that had ſo <hi>abuſed</hi> Them, and to diſ-ingage the <hi>Honour</hi> of Parliament from ſuch <hi>evill practices</hi> and <hi>deſignes</hi> of ſuch <hi>Incendiaries.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that after ſo manifeſt <hi>Remonſtrating</hi> to <hi>accuſe</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince</hi> them by <hi>particulars,</hi> what doth our <hi>Lawyer,</hi> but <hi>play the Jack,</hi> by crying out <hi>injuſtice, injury, iniquity,</hi> and <hi>illegality</hi> of proceeding, upon ſurmiſed grounds of the <hi>Armies</hi> mannaging the <hi>Charge</hi> in <hi>generall, ambiguous,</hi> and <hi>uncertaine</hi> termes, which they have thus <hi>publiquely</hi> diſclaimed?</p>
            <p>As to the other part of this <hi>Querie,</hi> wherein it is ſaid the <hi>King</hi> himſelfe hath given the <hi>lye</hi> to ſome of the Armies <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> touching his <hi>willingneſſe</hi> to remove from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> and Cornet <hi>Joyce</hi> his ſeizing his Perſon was a <hi>treaſonable Action.</hi> I ſhall not ſtand to juſtifie the <hi>Cornets</hi> Act as tolerable by the <hi>rigour</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> (by which only this confuſed <hi>Lay-Goſpeller</hi> condemnes it;) but if we looke upon the <hi>impulſive Cauſe</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing upon the Souldiery to attempt it, which was (as ſaies the laſt <hi>Declaration</hi>) the apprehenſion of <hi>private deſignes</hi> upon the <hi>King</hi> ere he came from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> to put his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of thoſe mens <hi>power,</hi> who ſought for the advantage of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> thereby to <hi>imbroyle</hi> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> in a <hi>new</hi> and <hi>bloudy</hi> War, and ſtrengthen themſelves in their <hi>miſchievous</hi> deſignes, the better to uphold their Faction, and intended <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> then we ſhall find that this <hi>ſeizing</hi> (or rather <hi>reſcue</hi>) of the <hi>Kings</hi> Perſon, was the very <hi>key of the worke,</hi> to locke up that <hi>Cabinet</hi> of ſecret Treaſons then and ſince diſcovered, which (like <hi>Pandora's Box</hi>) might elſe have repleniſhed the world with <hi>miſchiefes</hi> greater than before, and to unlocke that <hi>doore</hi> of <hi>future</hi> peace, which they and their <hi>confidents</hi> had barred up againſt the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> happineſſe: So that if Cornet <hi>Ioyce</hi> hath <hi>out-witted</hi> them, though in ſomewhat an <hi>irregular</hi> way againſt the <hi>Letter of the Law,</hi> yet I truſt this <hi>Nation</hi> will beare him out againſt all <hi>rigorous Lawyers,</hi> becauſe of the happy <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114285:5"/>and <hi>effect</hi> it will produce both to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> by ſetting a <hi>period</hi> to one <hi>tumultuous</hi> War, and hindring the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of a <hi>ſecond,</hi> which muſt neceſſarily have involved us in <hi>inevitable ruine.</hi> Nor do they yet give over the <hi>deſigne,</hi> but uſe all meanes to worke his <hi>Majeſty</hi> (whoſe wiſdome I doubt not is proofe againſt all <hi>flatteries</hi> tending to his ruine) to ingage and declare for them, or at leaſt to declare Himſelfe a <hi>priſoner,</hi> thereby to ſtir up His <hi>Party</hi> againſt the <hi>Army,</hi> who are the ſure <hi>Guardians</hi> of his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the fourth <hi>Querie,</hi> which is ſtuffed with a <hi>Rabble</hi> of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; as that it was but a <hi>pretence of the Army about falſe infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, miſ-repreſentations, and ſcandalous ſuggeſtions, made againſt them to the Houſe:</hi> For this I hope the <hi>Houſe</hi> will puniſh him in calling their <hi>wiſdome</hi> ſo far in queſtion, as to make the <hi>world</hi> beleeve ſo <hi>grave a Senate</hi> ſhould upon a <hi>meere pretence</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> retract one of their <hi>Declarations;</hi> and alſo right the <hi>Army</hi> from this ſcandall of <hi>pretence,</hi> by ſome reall <hi>example,</hi> to teſtifie a <hi>deteſtation</hi> of his <hi>abuſe</hi> both to <hi>Themſelves</hi> and the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo that the <hi>Army</hi> profeſſe <hi>ungratefully</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> touching the buſineſſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the ſecond, third, and fourth Articles of <hi>Charge.</hi> And what is it they profeſſe there, but that <hi>charity begins at home?</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>Iriſh deſigne</hi> to be but a <hi>Plot</hi> to breake in pieces the <hi>Army,</hi> to make way for the advancement of their <hi>Faction</hi> here to the <hi>oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>dedecoration</hi> of the <hi>Prince, Parliament,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> and to leave them in ſuch a <hi>lame</hi> abject condition, that the <hi>Clergy-lay Conventiclers</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> might in the meane while <hi>inſlave</hi> them beyond <hi>recovery,</hi> they could not without offering violence to their <hi>principles,</hi> as <hi>Engliſhmen;</hi> to their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> men; and to <hi>common piety,</hi> as lovers of their <hi>Countrey;</hi> but ſtay and ſee the <hi>Flocke</hi> ſecured from being made a <hi>prey</hi> to thoſe <hi>Woolves</hi> here, who might in a ſhort time have proved as bad as thoſe that had <hi>devoured the prey</hi> already in <hi>Ireland;</hi> whoſe laſt ruines muſt be put upon their <hi>ſcore,</hi> as thoſe who by <hi>under-hand</hi> practices have hindred thoſe many <hi>ſupplies,</hi> which might have been ſpeeded away long ago, to the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>redemption</hi> of that poore Kingdome.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114285:5"/>
            <p>To the fifth <hi>Querie,</hi> Whether <hi>the Army might not as well, by ſuch generall and uncertaine chargs, impeach the whole Houſe its ſelfe as well as thoſe eleven Members?</hi> This is more mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous than all the reſt, and calls aloud upon the <hi>Houſe</hi> to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate their <hi>Honour</hi> from ſo foule a <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> of <hi>guilt,</hi> which he endeavours to <hi>throw</hi> upon them all, equally with the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers impeached</hi> and their <hi>party,</hi> and endeavours to <hi>inſinuate</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mens minds, as if it were the <hi>caſe</hi> of the whole <hi>Houſe,</hi> which as it is contrarie to that <hi>reverence</hi> which the <hi>Army</hi> owes, and will expreſſe to the <hi>Worthies</hi> of the Houſe, ſo it requires the wiſdome of thoſe <hi>Worthies</hi> to correct the crafty <hi>ſawcineſſe</hi> of our <hi>Lawyer</hi> in vindication of their own <hi>credit,</hi> and terrifie other malepert <hi>Boutefeux</hi> of the <hi>faction</hi> from the like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacitie.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>parallelling</hi> the <hi>Kings demand</hi> of the <hi>five Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> heretofore and the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>eleven</hi> now, were it not time to leave off the mention of ought that may reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>him</hi> now, in a time when his <hi>honour</hi> and the <hi>Kingdomes peace</hi> are a repairing both together, I could manifeſt a great <hi>diſ-proportion</hi> (in regard of <hi>circumſtances</hi>) betwixt that <hi>act</hi> of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and this of the <hi>Army,</hi> and prove the invalidity of the <hi>inſtance.</hi> And whereas he prints that ordinary ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall in the mouthes of all that are of the <hi>faction,</hi> that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move of the <hi>impeached Members</hi> is endeavoured, onely that the <hi>Independent</hi> party might <hi>ſway and vote what they pleaſe;</hi> what is it but to yeeld that thoſe men were the <hi>heads</hi> of the <hi>faction,</hi> and held an <hi>influence</hi> on a great part of the <hi>Houſe</hi> to ſerve their owne <hi>deſigne?</hi> who the (<hi>Grandees</hi> being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne) may chance now to prove <hi>honeſt;</hi> which our <hi>furious Lawyer</hi> needed not to have <hi>exclaimed</hi> againſt ſo <hi>fearfully,</hi> if he had thought they had been ingaged upon ſuch <hi>principles</hi> before, as would have rendred them <hi>laſting friends</hi> to the <hi>faction:</hi> But now, they being gone, it's like every <hi>Bowie</hi> may run with its owne <hi>Byas,</hi> I mean <hi>conſcience,</hi> and every <hi>tub ſtand upon its owne bottome.</hi> Then ſure that will appeare but an <hi>ill cauſe,</hi> whoſe <hi>Fautors</hi> grow jealous of thriving by <hi>faire play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove board.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſixth <hi>Querie,</hi> Wherein he taxes the <hi>Army</hi> as quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114285:6"/>at the <hi>Houſes Votes,</hi> on purpoſe to keep from a <hi>diſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> to <hi>over-awe Parliament, City and Kingdome,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to throw all <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new</hi> elected Members out of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> that are not of their <hi>Party,</hi> with ſome <hi>exceptions</hi> alſo at the latter <hi>Elections</hi> in <hi>Cornwall, Wales, &amp;c.</hi> for the prevention of which, and the conquering thoſe other <hi>Gugawes</hi> rambled up in this ſixth <hi>Querie,</hi> our <hi>Lawyer</hi> deſires to <hi>awaken all honeſt men in time.</hi> And ſurely, had not men need of an <hi>awakening,</hi> the Presbyters <hi>faction</hi> had never been adorned with ſo many <hi>Proſelites</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> but now it is high time to open their eyes, that they may ſee who the men are, that have <hi>hoiſted</hi> up ſuch <hi>Votes</hi> by indirect means, on purpoſe to <hi>pick</hi> a <hi>quarrell</hi> with the <hi>Army,</hi> by putting them upon ſuch <hi>extraordinary</hi> waies for the <hi>ſafety</hi> of themſelves and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as in a time of leſſe <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>danger,</hi> they could not have adventured without a blemiſh of their <hi>Reputation:</hi> And it is ſo much the more <hi>trouble</hi> to them, to be reduced to this paſſe through the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty</hi> of their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> that they cannot aſſert the <hi>honour, freedome,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> but that they take occaſion to wreſt all their proceedings <hi>in Sequiorem,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them as <hi>Anti-Parliamentary,</hi> to the <hi>in-obſerving</hi> and more <hi>eaſie underſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As concerning the <hi>Elections</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> &amp;c. I had rather take the ſenſe of the <hi>Army,</hi> many of whom have been <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> there, than the opinion of <hi>our Lawyer,</hi> who pronounces them <hi>all faire,</hi> with as much <hi>confidence</hi> as if <hi>Mahomets Pidge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> gave him <hi>Intelligence</hi> from all <hi>corners</hi> of the world.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventh <hi>Querie</hi> he huddles over many <hi>Particulars</hi> of the ſame nature with thoſe in ſome of the <hi>former;</hi> and both the ſeventh and eighth containe nothing but matter of <hi>rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſcaudall,</hi> and <hi>miſrepreſentation,</hi> pretending that the <hi>Army</hi> acts againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their <hi>Priviledges,</hi> which I have ſufficiently refuted upon the former <hi>Queries;</hi> and <hi>ironically</hi> flouting them with the name of <hi>Saints, Saviours, Protectors,</hi> and the <hi>godly Party,</hi> telling them, they comply with the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants once in armes,</hi> complaining of the <hi>Breach of Articles,</hi> and <hi>craving reparation for their wrongs,</hi> &amp;c. But he never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders, that equity is due to our worſt <hi>enemies;</hi> and being loth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114285:6"/>to give the Army the honour of their <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>equitable</hi> intentions, never tells upon what gronnd they are thus <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate</hi> to their <hi>quondam-Adverſaries;</hi> which certainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes as much <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> together with hope of <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as can poſſibly be imagined, by a <hi>due conſideration of the right, quiet, and immunity of His Majeſty, his royall Family, &amp; late Partakers; ſuppoſing a ſpirit</hi> of <hi>common love</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> diffuſing it ſelfe to the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>preſervation</hi> of All, wil be the <hi>only</hi> way to make up the <hi>moſt glorious</hi> Conqueſt over their <hi>hearts</hi> (if <hi>God in mercy</hi> ſee it good) to make <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>whole People of the Land laſting Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the main <hi>Scandal</hi> in the eight <hi>Querie</hi> is a <hi>ſtory</hi> wherein he <hi>parallels</hi> the proceedings of the <hi>Army</hi> with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> at <hi>Munſter,</hi> with the ſame <hi>ungracious</hi> impudence, as he does by the Rebellion of <hi>Iack Cade</hi> in the ſecond <hi>Querie,</hi> and ſo gives the <hi>City</hi> an <hi>Alarm</hi> to <hi>ſtand upon their Guard.</hi> It's well you'l be content with that <hi>poſture</hi> now, but certain it is, the <hi>Deſigne,</hi> when it was firſt <hi>conceived</hi> in darknes, and the <hi>privy Iunto</hi> of <hi>Confederates</hi> had <hi>travailed</hi> with it a whole night, was <hi>brought forth</hi> in the morning, a fair <hi>Cockney</hi> with the <hi>face</hi> of a <hi>new warr;</hi> which was <hi>nourſt</hi> up very <hi>carefully</hi> for a few daies, till the <hi>Citizens</hi> ſaw it would prove a very <hi>chargeable brat,</hi> and ſo it was immediatly <hi>ſmothered.</hi> I appland their <hi>wiſedom,</hi> that they were able to ſee themſelves made but a <hi>ſtalking-horſe</hi> to ſerve other mens <hi>private ends;</hi> and I cannot but commend their <hi>reſolution</hi> to free themſelves from all ſuch like <hi>purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milking</hi> Complots for the <hi>future,</hi> which tend only to draw on the <hi>guilt</hi> of <hi>innocent</hi> blood, and <hi>draine</hi> the <hi>publick</hi> treaſure of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> to ſupport the <hi>ambitious intereſts</hi> of <hi>particular</hi> men. And as for the <hi>Army,</hi> I doubt not but all men of this famons City <hi>unintereſted</hi> (or not wrought upon and amuſed by perſons <hi>Intereſted</hi>) are really ſatisfyed with their <hi>candid</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> Intentions towards this <hi>City,</hi> ſo often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>declared</hi> and <hi>remonſtrated:</hi> And if through the <hi>ſeditious</hi> provocations of ſuch <hi>furies</hi> as our <hi>Lawyer,</hi> they entertaine a <hi>cauſeleſſe jealouſie,</hi> and be urged thereby to act in prejudice of the Army, that <hi>paſſionate</hi> love which I beare to the <hi>renown</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of this <hi>delight of the Nation,</hi> makes me tremble to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114285:7"/>think into what <hi>fatall Conſequences</hi> ſuch curſed <hi>Counſellours</hi> would <hi>allure</hi> and <hi>inſnare</hi> them: And therefore they had beſt be well adviſed, that they behave themſelves with ſuch <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> as to do nothing but in order to their owne <hi>defence,</hi> from the injuries of <hi>diſcontented</hi> enemies within, and without the leaſt ſhadow of <hi>provocation</hi> to their friends without, it reſting upon their wiſe <hi>carriage,</hi> either to burie the <hi>ſeeds</hi> of <hi>warre, ſedition</hi> and <hi>tumult,</hi> in an honourable <hi>Peace,</hi> or the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> in a <hi>new Rupture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ninth and laſt <hi>Querie,</hi> wherein he taxes the <hi>Armies</hi> demand of a ſpeedy <hi>Anſwer</hi> to their <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> to be the <hi>higheſt, arroganteſt, and unreaſonableſt that ever was propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall ſay no more but this, that <hi>neceſſity</hi> admits of no <hi>delay</hi> in <hi>Affaires</hi> of this nature, ſeeing it were as much as to put themſelves to the <hi>hazzard</hi> of an <hi>After-game,</hi> when their <hi>enemies</hi> are <hi>viſibly</hi> active upon the <hi>Counter-plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſhall conclude only with one <hi>Anti-querie,</hi> in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his nine <hi>Queries,</hi> viz: Whether if the <hi>Author</hi> of thoſe <hi>impudent, falſe,</hi> and <hi>ſeditious Queries,</hi> have no <hi>eares</hi> to loſe, hee deſerve not to bee <hi>cramp't</hi> in that <hi>right Thumb,</hi> which hath heretofore condemned ſo much <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Divinity</hi> to <hi>confuſion;</hi> and now at laſt, moſt <hi>impiouſly</hi> ſcandalized our <hi>beſt friends,</hi> as enemies of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
